בוקר טוב, Boker tov, we are doing today דף ס"ט, daf samech
tes, 69, and we pick up at the four lines from the
top at the two dots.
Yesterday, I mean there's been a lot of discussion in the last
few days about like what types of קניינים kinyanim work for גניבה,
geneiva, you know first the whole question about things that aren't a
full שינוי מעשה shinui ma'aseh vs שינוי השם, shinui hashem, the name
changes but it's not to an action and is it חוזר לבריאתו,
chozer livriyaso, does it go back to the way it was? Is
there been יאוש ye'ush that accompanied it? I wasn't actually there for
that day but important question is, you know the גמרא Gemara at
a certain stage spoke of שינוי השם shinui hashem with יאוש. ye'ush.
And the question was was that did you somehow need them both
working together or was it that the יאוש ye'ush allowed the שינוי
השם shinui hashem to take place? Since the original owner had given
up hope that allowed the גנב ganav to be מקדיש makdish it,
that allowed the גנב ganav to designate what he was going to
use that piece of leather for, right, otherwise his designation wouldn't have
any significance if the owner had not yet been מיאש me'yaesh but
ultimately the יאוש ye'ush was a means and what the קניין kinyun
worked was through שינוי השם shinui hashem and then we had of
course a long discussions about whether יאוש ye'ush works and does יאוש
ye'ush work by itself or not to have the גנב ganav own
it. And then the גמרא Gemara after having gone through all of
that and all of the implications of that had a whole another
discussion which essentially was the same debate but it was from the
other perspective because the other discussion that we had yesterday was the
question about what are the circumstances under which a גנב ganav is
חייב chayav for slaughtering or selling the animal. So slaughtering it's basically
all circumstances but the question is selling and there is it that
it's only after and is the reason there because you just repeated
the thing, שנה בחטא, shana bacheit, or is the way the other
approach is נשתרש בחטא, nishtarshe bacheit, you actually gave the sin more
teeth, you made it more permanent. So and the גמרא Gemara says
that that would play itself out in terms of whether you're only
חייב chayav for מכירה mechira after יאוש. ye'ush. One approach is you're
חייב chayav for מכירה mechira whenever even if it was before יאוש
ye'ush and you sold it and the owner can retrieve it so
you weren't נשתרש בחטא, nishtarshe bacheit, you didn't give it roots, they're
going to get their object back but you repeated the sin. So
whereas if you need to give the sin roots right then the
selling you're only חייב chayav after יאוש ye'ush and now the owner
cannot retrieve his object. So that was this debate but of course
that assumed that after יאוש ye'ush definitely you're חייב chayav and it
assumed that יאוש ye'ush by itself wasn't קונה. koneh. So some of
this questions about when are you חייב chayav for מכירה mechira before
only before יאוש ye'ush because after יאוש, ye'ush, יאוש ye'ush is קונה,
koneh, only after יאוש ye'ush because it's an idea of נשתרש בחטא,
nishtarshe bacheit, right, and therefore the נשתרש בחטא nishtarshe bacheit only happens
after יאוש ye'ush or both before and after יאוש, ye'ush, right? So
there are those three possibilities when you're חייב chayav for מכירה mechira
and to some degree which ones of them are possible depends on
whether you think יאוש ye'ush is קונה koneh or not. So we
had the same type of debate yesterday whether יאוש ye'ush was קונה
koneh but not directly through the lens of יאוש, ye'ush, through the
lens of understanding what are the obligations for slaughtering and selling. So
that's where we sort of left off having looked explored the different
קניינים kinyanim and explored the parameters the reasons behind why you're חייב
chayav for slaughtering and selling and the implications of that of selling
before and after יאוש. ye'ush. Yes, Michael.
You're saying that the words שלא חוטא נשכר shelo hotei niskar never
came up in this discussion. Right. Saying that I mean would think
that that'd be some sort of
why is he נשכר niskar that he wouldn't be paying for a
fine?
Well or like you know someone steals from him and in this
case that he would potentially get something you know what I mean?
Yeah I mean it's an interesting point. I mean most of these
things the question was are you חייב chayav for a fine or
not? You're not נשכר niskar you're just not being imposed an additional
fine. But it is interesting yeah I can't give you an answer
like when the גמרא Gemara decides to you know reference that principle.
Of course I know that's the type of גמרא Gemara you love,
right? So anyway now we pick up okay with now that so
we're done with sort of that overview of
and now we look up as Michael correctly referenced in that discussion
of selling and is it before after יאוש ye'ush and so on
there was also discussion which got to the next point of the
משנה mishna which is stealing from the house of the גנב. ganav.
That if you steal from the house of the גנב ganav you
don't pay כפל. keifail. You don't pay it to the גנב ganav
because he doesn't own it yet. If he does own it you
would pay him כפל. keifail. But if he doesn't you won't pay
him כפל, keifail, it's not his. But the חידוש chiddush of the
משנה mishna is you don't even pay the owner כפל keifail when
you steal it from the house of the גנב ganav because it
says וגונב מבית האיש, v'gunav mibeis ha'ish, from the person's house. And
once it is outside of his house, house could be used figuratively,
control, right? If I have you watch my object for me and
somebody steals it they're going to have to pay me כפל. keifail.
It's still מבית האיש mibeis ha'ish if it's in your house because
you're watching it for me. But if it's out of my house
figuratively, it's out of my control, if it's been stolen away okay
I mean and somebody is stealing it from the גנב ganav then
there's not going to be כפל. keifail. So this now puts us
to the next stage of our discussion which is the status of
an object not in the house of the owner. The גנב ganav
isn't קונה, koneh, יאוש ye'ush isn't קונה, koneh, but it's out of
my control, what are the implications of that? And one is that
you don't pay כפל. kefel. Okay.
And I'm sorry, if you're a שומר חינם, shomer chinam, I give
you my object, שומר חינם, shomer chinam, because of פשיעה, peshiah, stolen
from you, right?
So now so what happens?
The גנב ganav pays you כפל. kefel.
So why wouldn't you say that you're חייב chayav because of פשיעה
peshiah to pay me?
Yeah, I I might be, but he's also but I mean you
know, if he winds up being found or whatever, then I don't
have to pay you because then you didn't lose your object.
But if he wasn't found, then I pay you for losing the
object.
And if the גנב ganav is later found, he pays you?
No, he pays you the כפל.
kefel. I mean you pay me the כפל? kefel?
I don't know, either he pays whatever, but I get my money
back. All right, anyway, that's a בבא מציעא Bava Metzia question. גופא.
Gufa. Let's take a look now four lines from the top in
בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. Okay, גופא, Gufa, it's on ע"ד ע"א. ayin
daled amud aleph. So אמר ר' יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, Rabbi Yochanan
says גזל ולא נתייאשו הבעלים, gezel velo nityashu habalim, if you have
something stolen and the owners have not given up hope of getting
it back, שניהם אינם יכולים להקדיש, sheneihem einam yecholim lehakdish,
both cannot sanctify it. זה לפי שאינו שלו, ze lefi she'eino shelo,
the גזלן gazlan obviously because it's not his, וזה לפי שאינו ברשותו,
veze lefi she'eino birshuto, and the owner because it's not under his
control. So he's taking this idea that it's not בבית האיש beveit
ha'ish and the same way that there is an implication that if
it's stolen from the גזלן gazlan that there's no כפל, kefel, if
there's no בבית האיש, beveit ha'ish, if it's not in my control
that has other implications. I can't I can't exercise my rights as
owners and therefore I can't sanctify it, presumably I can't sell it,
I can't do the normal types of things I have rights to
as an owner because it's out of my control. Okay, so let's
take a look. So גמרא Gemara says ומי אמר ר' יוחנן הכי,
umi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi, did he really say this? ואמר ר'
יוחנן ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan הלכה כסתם משנה, halacha kistam mishna, we rule
like a סתם משנה. stam mishna. ותנן, vetnan, and here is a
משנה mishna we have.
It says in מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, כרם רבעי, Kerem Revai, if
you have fruit growing in its fourth year, היו מציינים אותו בצרורות
אדמה, hayu metzaynim oto betzrorot adamah, you would you would mark it
in your field, you'd put like these clumps of earth around your
orchard of כרם רבעי Kerem Revai or your vineyard so people should
know that it's כרם רבעי. Kerem Revai. Now of course why do
you want people to know? You might want to do it to
remind yourself, okay, but also what the גמרא Gemara seems is going
to be saying or the משנה mishna is going to be saying
is that in case people come and they steal your fruit, at
least they should know that not to also misuse its halachic status
and know that what they're stealing is כרם רבעי. Kerem Revai. Okay,
and now the גמרא Gemara one minute, let's finish this. The גמרא
Gemara now interjects, you can actually it's interesting, you can see the
shift to Aramaic where the גמרא Gemara then is glossing the symbolic
significance of these various markers. So גמרא Gemara says סימנא, simana, the
symbol is, כי אדמה, ki adamah,
it's like dirt. מה אדמה אית לה הנאה מינה, ma adamah it
la hana'ah minah, the same way dirt there's benefit because you plant
in the ground, אף האי נמי, af hai nami, so this כרם
רבעי Kerem Revai as well, the fourth year of the of the
vineyard,
right, it's a vineyard, it's not נטע רבעי, Neta Revai, אף האי
נמי כי מפרקא, af hai nami ki mifreka, when you redeem it,
שרי לאיתהנויי מיניה, shari le'itanuyei mineih, you can get benefits from it.
It's not forbidden in benefit, but it has to be either eaten
in ירושלים Yerushalayim or it has to be redeemed. So that you
סימנא, simana, that you mark with these clumps of earth. ושל ערלה,
veshel orlah, if you have a patch of your, you know, of
your vineyard or of your orchard that's ערלה, orlah, so how do
you what do you do there to mark that? בחרסית, becharsit, with
a piece of pottery. And here the גמרא Gemara shifts here it
shifts to Aramaic, now the גמרא's Gemara talking, סימנא, simana, the symbol
is, כחרסית, kecharsit, like pottery. מה חרסית שאין הנאה מינה, ma charsit
she'ein hana'ah minah, the same way like a broken piece of shard
of pottery there's no benefit you can get from it, אף האי
דלית ביה הנאה מיניה, af hai deleit beih hana'ah mineih, so this
pottery says this is completely off-limits, now you can't get any benefit,
it's ערלה. orlah. ושל קברות, veshel kevarot,
and if you have a patch in your yard in your field
that somebody was buried in, so בסיד, besid, you would you would
pour plaster around it. סימנא, simana, now the גמרא Gemara interjects, the
symbol is, דחיורא כעצמות, dechivra ke'atzmot, as white as bones. Okay, ומבחוץ
ושופך, umibachutz veshofech, back to the משנה, mishna, you'd like mix it
with water and pour and you know pour out the the the
plaster around the grave, כי היכי דנחוור טפי, ki heichi denachvir tefei,
and it's so interesting you see switching from the Hebrew to the
Aramaic, Gemara says because you want it really white, okay, so anyway
you want it to be very visible to כהנים. Kohanim. All right,
that's the משנה, mishna, people would mark their fields in these various
ways. אמר רשב"ג, Amar Rashbag, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says, במה דברים
אמורים, bamah devarim amorim, when is it that you have this obligation,
now the משנה mishna never said you had an obligation, it just
was describing a practice. But רשב"ג Rashbag says, like when is this
practice appropriate? בשביעית, beshvi'it, during the שמיטה shmita year. הפקר hefker נינהו,
ninhu, again switching to the גמרא's Gemara comment, because it's הפקר hefker
and therefore people have a right to go and take the stuff,
so they should know, hey, you're about to take the fruit and
you have a right to because it's שמיטה, shmita, but this is
ערלה, orlah, you can't eat this, don't take this, this is כרם
רבעי, Kerem Revai, make sure you redeem it, etc. Okay, okay, so
that's we then you would care about people misusing your fruit because
because what they're doing is is permissible. אבל בשאר שני שבוע, aval
bish'ar shenei shavu'a, the rest of the seven-year
cycle. הלעיטהו לרשע וימות, Haliteihu l'rasha v'yamot, let, you know, pour it,
there you go, Michael, for your חוטא נדקר. chotei nidkar. Pour it
down the רשע's rasha throat and let him die, okay, which is
like, you know, if somebody is sinning and they're bringing it upon
themselves, you do not have a responsibility to intervene and to help
this person, which is like a fascinating, you know, moral question or
religious question about that, right? Like, okay, he's doing one עבירה, aveira,
should I, you know, why shouldn't I at least stop them, I
mean one imagines for example if it was literally that they were
endangering themselves, you know, like, you know, here's a question, like, should
you, you know, should you sort of be encouraging the use of
condoms because for people, you know, who are like, you know, anyway
having premarital sex and you say like, oh you know what if
they get a venereal disease or whatever, you know, they brought it
upon themselves, right? Which obviously are some way some people's attitude is.
Do you say look, just because somebody is doing one thing wrong
doesn't mean that you don't have to act in a way, you
know, and you shouldn't, right, giving needles to drug users, right? So,
yeah, just because they're doing one thing wrong they should be, you
know, have to live with the consequences of that even if it
creates a health hazard and so on. So the question is, okay,
but you know that's a real like health hazard, right, that's a
real like protecting their life and their health. Okay, but here, you
know, he might be saying like, look, you know, they're doing an
עבירה aveira and you don't have the responsibility to stop that from
leading to another עבירה.
aveira. But what's the עבירה aveira they're doing?
Yeah, they're stealing from you. It's not שמיטה. Shmita. Why do they
need to know about what your fruit is? Right, so they're stealing
from you.
So don't put in markers like that, then no one gets anything,
right, because you're not allowed to,
you don't do any marking of your field, presumably you know, you're
not marking it for your sake. So you don't bother marking it
for other people's sake because the only reason the other people would
need to know is if they were stealing your stuff.
No, no, but that's what I'm saying, so there's no פאה, pe'ah,
right, because it's רבעי, revai, because don't you have to usually give
part of your...
Oh, oh, that's interesting. Yeah, I mean, would it... so it's not
that they're necessarily stealing, you're right, maybe they came into my field
because they're doing מתנות עניים matnot aniyim from the vineyard. No, but
but the עבירה aveira is not trespassing, the עבירה aveira is stealing.
Okay, this is stuff that they don't have a right to take.
In a scenario where they would have a right to take, it
was לקט שכחה leket shikcha or something of that... but you're right,
it's not, because the whole thing was רבעי. revai. Yeah,
yeah, you're right, okay, yeah.
Yeah, I was just going to say there's a distinction between individual
responsibility, like, I wouldn't say it's your responsibility to go around giving
sterile needles to drug users in your neighborhood. That might be the
government's responsibility.
So it's like, how much, right, and this seems to be like,
and also it seems to be like this was a practice that
was a standard practice and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel is actually like trying to like almost go against it, say
you shouldn't be doing it under these circumstances. I think the other
question is, look, what's the argument, let's use the example about the
drug needles. What's the counter-argument? The counter-argument is that if you do
that, you're just encouraging people to do it. The signal you're signaling
to them is, oh, this is okay, this is acceptable and so
on. And that might also be part of his point, which is
if you're going to go ahead and put up some type of
a marker, but the only purpose is for people who are stealing
they should know what it is, it's like, you're sort of saying,
oh, so you're okay that we're
stealing. Or, you know, oh, the only עבירה aveira that matters is
the בין אדם למקום bein adam l'makom עבירה aveira of ערלה. orlah.
בין אדם לחבירו bein adam l'chavero like that doesn't matter, you know.
So it's... there could be questions about the types of messages you're
sending, but it's... I think it's a really fascinating position, yeah.
I would just put pottery on all of my fields
and then they'd think it's all ערלה, orlah, right, and keep off
of the whole thing, exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay,
וימות. v'yamot. והצנועין, V'hatzenuin, now the... you know, צנוע tzanua is modest,
but here it sort of means the people that are like, it's
a little bit like חסידות. Hasidut. Right, right, it's like the people
that are very פרום frum in the... not in the contemporary category
of פרום frum which often has to do more with like whatever,
other types of things, ways of physically demarcating that you're different from
other people, you know, through dress and food etc., צנועין tzenuin here
like a type of a pious. Okay, you know, the pious ones,
who care for other people's behalf even if they're going ahead and
stealing, והצנועין, v'hatzenuin, what do they do? Not only do they mark
the stuff, but they take extra precautions. מניחין את המעות, Manichin et
hamaot, they put money aside, ואומרין, v'omrin, because again, and they say,
they can't help it if people take the ערלה, orlah, but I
can help it if people take the כרם רבעי. kerem revai. And
they can say, כל הנלקט מזה מחולל על המעות הללו, kol hanilkat
mizeh mechulal al hamaot halalu, anything that's taken from the vineyard, this
כרם רבעי, kerem revai, should be transferred to this money, and therefore
if they steal it and they ignore the סימן, siman, at least
they won't be eating this כרם רבעי kerem revai outside of ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. Okay, now how is this relevant to us? It's relevant in
the following way. If they are saying that once it is picked
let it be redeemed on this money, at that stage it's out
of their control, and they're doing this act that is an act
of exercising their ownership rights, they're redeeming it, that's something that an
owner can do, and they're exercising their rights after
it's
no... So
the
גמרא Gemara starts that the question is obvious, right? How are you
able to do this according to רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? וכי תימא,
V'chi teima, if you say מאן תנא צנועין רבי שמעון בן גמליאל,
man tana tznuin Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel, maybe the comment about the
צנועין tznuin was all part of the quote marks within רבי שמעון
בן גמליאל. Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel. רבי שמעון בן גמליאל Rabbi Shimon
ben Gamliel would say, if it's during the rest of the year,
let them let them eat it and do, and and kill themselves
religiously. But the צנועין tznuin are here's what the צנועין tznuin do.
So it was רבי שמעון בן גמליאל'ס Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel's claim
of what the צנועין tznuin did, but it is not actually the
סתם stam voice of the משנה. Mishna. And that's relevant because רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't have to agree with every תנא, tana, but
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan פוסקנס paskens like a סתם משנה, stam Mishna,
and like that's how the גמרא Gemara introduced it. So you cannot
have the סתם משנה stam Mishna recording what the צנועין tznuin did
implying that what the צנועין tznuin did worked. Okay, but it could
have רבי שמעון בן גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel saying that this
is what the צנועין tznuin did. So וכי תימא מאן תנא צנועין
רבי שמעון בן גמליאל. V'chi teima man tana tznuin Rabbi Shimon ben
Gamliel. No, ואמר רבה בר בר חנה רבי יוחנן, v'amar Rabba bar
bar Chana Rabbi Yochanan, כל מקום ששנה רבי שמעון בן גמליאל במשנתנו
kol makom sheshana Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel bemishnateinu or no,
meaning yes, even if it were true, it wouldn't matter. Because רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan has another פסק—the psak same way he פוסקנס paskens
we go like a סתם משנה, stam Mishna, he says whenever רבי
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel appears in our משנה, Mishna,
הלכה כמותו, Halacha k'moto, we rule like him, חוץ משלש—except chutz mishalosh
for three exceptions: ערב, arev, the case of a co-signer; צידן, Tzidan,
which is a case of witnesses or whatever and they were in
a certain place; וראיה אחרונה, v'raaya achrona, and a last proof. Okay,
I won't go into what those three are, but anyway, even if
it were רבי שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel, we would
פוסקן pasken like it. So here's a משנה Mishna of what the
צנועין tznuin do. One way or the other, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
would say we would פוסקן pasken that. It's a סתם משנה stam
Mishna or רבי שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel. And that
seems to be able to exercise your control as an owner even
when it's out of your רשות. reshut. Okay, your rights as an
owner even when it's out of your control. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אלא, ela,
fine, the גמרא Gemara says אמרי לא תימא כל הנלקט מזה, amri
lo teima kol hanilkat mizeh, fine, don't read it, as Michael was
suggesting, anything that will be picked will be redeemed, and then the
redemption occurs after the עניים aniyim have already taken it and after
it's been stolen. אלא אימא כל המתלקט מזה, ela eima kol hamitlaket
mizeh,
anything that will be picked from this. Okay, so because of that,
you are now, it's—the redemption is happening now based on what happens
later, based on which things are picked. Right, תוספות Tosafot says, one
thing I don't understand, why don't you just redeem the whole darn
vineyard? Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says, no, you want to bring the
the stuff to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. You don't want to redeem the whole
thing. Or תוספות Tosafot says maybe more will grow and you want—the
redemption won't work on the stuff that's going to grow later. You
only want to redeem right now the stuff you have to. Okay,
so you don't know which part they're going to take if they
come in and they take stuff they're not allowed. So you'll say,
"the stuff that will turn out that they took, that'll be the
stuff that right now I'm redeeming." Okay, it's a type of a
ברירה. breira. I don't know which part of the field they'll take
from, but whichever part that will be, that'll be redeemed on this
money. תוספות Tosafot also points out the גמרא Gemara has to be
assuming that that you can redeem stuff while it's still connected to
the ground, where we normally assume you couldn't. Right, if you said
only after it's been picked you redeem it, then then that's obvious.
But here now you're redeeming it while it's still connected to the
ground based on what happens later. Okay, so that's how you're going
to do it. And that's a ברירה breira type of an idea
and that's while it's still under your control. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? umi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi?
But how could רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say that? ואמר רבי יוחנן
צנועין ורבי דוסא אמרו דבר אחד. v'amar Rabbi Yochanan tznuin v'Rabbi Dosa
amru davar echad. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says the צנועין tznuin of
this משנה Mishna and רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa we're about to see
say the same הלכה, Halacha, the same position. What's the רבי דוסא?
Rabbi Dosa? ורבי דוסא נלקט קאמר. v'Rabbi Dosa nilkat ka'amar. It's clear
that רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa is talking about when you say it
after it's been picked and not beforehand. How do you know? דתניא,
detanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braita, רבי יהודה אומר שחרית—shacharit Rabbi
Yehuda omer shacharit was Michael's case, it's your case where somebody is
going in because they have a right to collect, to pick. The
issue here is not your כרם רבעי kerem revai and ערלה, orlah,
the עניים aniyim should not be collecting from that field, they don't,
you know, לקט שכחה פאה leket shikcha peah don't apply. But let's
say,
forget the question
of ערלה orlah and all these הלכתיק Halachic statuses. The עניים aniyim
are coming into your field, they're collecting the grain, but they're only
allowed to collect by לקט, leket, stalks that were dropped if one
or two stalks were dropped. If three stalks were dropped in the
same place, they're not allowed to collect that. Okay, and not all
the עניים aniyim know the rule and not all עניים aniyim care
about the rule. So you're now concerned that you don't want them
to become to be הלכתיקלי Halachically seen as into גזלנים. gazlanim. You
want to, you know like the story with the חפץ חיים. Chafetz
Chaim. You know that somebody steals something from his house, you know,
whatever, and he's running after the guy and he's saying, I'm מוחל,
mochel, I'm מוחל. mochel. So, you know, so this is the story:
they're stealing, they're going to steal, but you know the עניים, aniim,
so you want to be, you want to let them take it.
Okay, also תוספות Tosafot points out, there actually is another sort of
more of the, you know, כשרות kashrut types of issues, you know,
in terms of issues here because
if it's not הפקר, hefker,
then if when they pick it up, it's not yet הפקר hefker
and you're only מפקיר mafkir it afterwards or whatever, then there's a
problem that they're obligated to give תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot from it,
you know? But if they pick it up and it's הפקר, hefker,
then when you take something out of הפקר hefker from הפקר, hefker,
you don't have to give תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot from it. So
that's the concern here. So let's take a look. רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer, שחרית shacharit in the morning,
בעל הבית baal habayit עומד ואומר, omed ve'omer, כל שילקטו עניים יהא
הפקר. kol she'yilketu aniim yehei hefker. Anything that עניים aniim will pick
will be הפקר. hefker. Okay? רבי דוסא אומר, Rabbi Dosa omer, no,
no, no, לעתותי ערב le'itotei erev right towards nightfall אומר, omer, כל
שלקטו עניים יהא הפקר. kol she'laktu aniim yehei hefker. Anything they did
pick will be הפקר. hefker. So we don't exactly know why they're
debating, but we'll see, maybe we'll explore that in a minute. But
if רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai says, then רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, excuse me, that the צנועים tznuim and רבי
דוסא Rabbi Dosa say the same thing. So רבי דוסא's Rabbi Dosa
point is explicitly, you do it after the thing has taken place.
And now you have two positions that seem to be that you
can exercise your control to be מפקיר mafkir something or to redeem
something after it's out of your control. Your rights, but you exercise
it after it's out of your control. So the גמרא Gemara says
איפכא, ipcha, fine, let's reverse it. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda to רבי
דוסא, Rabbi Dosa, ורבי דוסא ve'Rabbi Dosa to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
Have רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda be the one that says you do
it at night and רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa the one that says
you do it in the morning. And therefore the רבי דוסא Rabbi
Dosa and the צנועים tznuim will have you saying that you do
this before the stuff gets picked and while it's still under your
control. So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי אפכת מתניתין, amai apchat matnitin,
why did you reverse the ברייתא? braita? אפכה לרבי יוחנן, apcha le'Rabbi
Yochanan, why not just say רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, the statement we
have in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan got the names
mixed up? ואימא, ve'eima, have רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan be saying צנועים
ורבי יהודה אמרו דבר אחד. tznuim ve'Rabbi Yehuda amru davar echad. Right?
We're still working that the only way to explain the צנועים tznuim
position is that they did it in the morning. So, but רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan got us in trouble because he said it was
like רבי דוסא. Rabbi Dosa. So fine, have him say we got
that version wrong, what he meant to say was it was like
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says also here,
by being מפקיר mafkir the stuff that the עניים aniim are going
to pick up, you're doing it in the morning. Okay, so why
are you switching רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa and רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
Just say רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan got the wrong name, or the
name was recorded wrong, it was רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So אמרי,
amri, no, you can say לא סגיא דלאו מהפכת מתניתין. lo sagya
d'lav mahpachat matnitin. No, no, no, forget the whole רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan piece here, we anyway had to reverse the names in the
ברייתא. braita. Why did you have to reverse the names in the
ברייתא? braita? דבהא מתניתין קתני דאית ליה לרבי יהודה ברירה. de'v'ha matnitin
katani de'it lei le'Rabbi Yehuda breira. So
here the גמרא Gemara now is going to get to what difference
does it make in the morning or in the evening. And this
is what we mentioned before, the issue of ברירה. breira. In
the evening, the problem is that it's not under your control. That's
the רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan problem. In the morning, the problem is
you don't know which grain you're talking about yet, right? So therefore,
if who the,
that could be the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי
דוסא. Rabbi Dosa. So in the version we have of the ברייתא,
braita, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you do
it in the morning, which means he holds of ברירה, breira, right?
Because you don't know yet, it will be determined later. But we
know in general רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does
say... דבהא מתניתין de'v'ha matnitin קתני דאית ליה לרבי יהודה ברירה. katani
de'it lei le'Rabbi Yehuda breira. In the version we have of the
ברייתא, braita, רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda saying you're doing it in the
morning, which means he holds of ברירה. breira. But that doesn't work.
ושמעינן ליה לרבי יהודה בעלמא דלית ליה ברירה. ve'shaminah lei le'Rabbi Yehuda
be'alma de'leit lei breira. We know in general רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
does say he doesn't hold of ברירה. breira. דתנן, de'tnan, as we
taught, הלוקח יין מבין הכותים. halokeach yayin mibein ha'kutim.
Somebody is purchasing wine from Samaritans. Okay, where it's like a type
of a, what do you call it? Of a דמאי, demai, you're
not sure whether they've already taken תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'maasrot from it.
So, and it's בין השמשות bein hashmashot on שבת. Shabbat. Now what
do you say in במה מדליקין bameh madlikin for those who say
במה מדליקין, bameh madlikin, right? ספק חשיכה ספק אינה חשיכה אין מעשרין
את הודאי אבל מעשרין את הדמאי. safek chasheicha safek einah chasheicha ein
maasrin et havadai aval maasrin et hademai.
You don't take מעשר maaser from stuff that definitely requires תרומות ומעשרות,
trumot u'maasrot, but you can take it from stuff that doubtfully, that
might require תרומות ומעשרות. trumot u'maasrot. So you've got this, it's ערב
שבת בין השמשות. erev Shabbat bein hashmashot. You do not have a
lot of time. Okay, you cannot have time to start measuring out
ten percent for this מעשר maaser and then another ten percent for
the other מעשר. maaser. You gotta do it quick, שבת Shabbat is
about to start. So here's what you say. אומר, omer, שני לוגין
שאני עתיד להפריש. shnei lugin she'ani atid lehafrish.
The two לוג log that I will eventually separate out of this
wine... we're going to assume you have like 102 לוג, log, you
know, gallons or
whatever... actually it's much less. 102 whatever, I don't know, quarts. Okay,
so the two quarts that I will eventually separate, הרי הן תרומה.
harei hen truma. They're תרומה truma because normally תרומה truma is about
two percent. Now you're left with a hundred. עשרה asara so the
next 10 quarts that I will separate out after שבת shabbos מעשר
ראשון maaser rishon they are right now מעשר ראשון. maaser rishon. תשעה
tesha next nine because now you're left with ninety, so 10 percent
of the remaining 90 is 9, is מעשר שני. maaser sheni. So
right now I'm separating תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros on which stuff? That'll
be determined after שבת shabbos based on the stuff that I select
after שבת. shabbos. That'll be the stuff that I'm sanctifying right now.
Okay? ומחל ושותה מיד u'mechal v'shoseh miyad and you can begin to
drink immediately. רש"י rashi questions what the word מחל mechal means. Either
it means just מתחיל ושותה מיד maschil v'shoseh miyad or as or
quoting רש"י rashi says you redeem the מעשר שני maaser sheni stuff
onto money. Anyway, that's what you do. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei rabbi
meir. That's what Rabbi Meir says. So that's a classic ברירה. breira.
Right now I'm taking תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros on what stuff? The
stuff I'll designate later. Okay, רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אוסרים.
rabbi yehuda v'rabbi yose v'rabbi shimon osrim. They say no, you're not
allowed to do it, it doesn't work. So you see that רבי
יהודה rabbi yehuda doesn't hold of ברירה. breira. Now there's another possible
reason why they don't like it which I'll get to in a
minute, but you see he doesn't hold of ברירה. breira. Okay, so
we've got though the ברייתא braisa too
much and then right or right,
so the we'll get to that. So the ברייתא braisa though says
that רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda says you say in the morning I
מפקיר mafkir what they'll pick. So that's a ברירה breira issue. So
we anyway had to reverse the names in the ברייתא. braisa. Okay,
so the גמרא gemara says so where are we right now? We're
that רבי יוחנן, rabbi yochanan, you have the צנועים tznuim who are
who are redeeming it once it's already stolen. That doesn't work for
רבי יוחנן. rabbi yochanan. So we're having them say, okay, so what
they really said is they did a ברירה breira thing. They didn't
say it after it was stolen, they did it in the morning.
And that רבי יוחנן rabbi yochanan now רבי יוחנן rabbi yochanan also
said that they say the same thing as רבי דוסא. rabbi dosa.
So anyway we had to reverse names in this ברייתא braisa so
we have רבי דוסא rabbi dosa as well saying that the בעל
הבית baal habayis would be מפקיר mafkir his stuff in the morning
that the עניים aniyim would come and take that they didn't have
a right to. Okay, so we have him saying it in the
morning and based on ברירה. breira. So the גמרא's gemara saying, but
it's still not going to work. אמרי, amri, סוף סוף sof sof
at the end of the day,
אמאי אהפכת לה למתניתין amai ahepchata lah l'masnisin why are you reversing
the ברייתא? braisa? משום דקשיא דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה. mishum d'kashya d'rabbi
yehuda a'drabbi yehuda. You said because רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda clearly doesn't
hold of ברירה breira and in the ברייתא braisa he does hold
of ברירה, breira, so we gotta reverse the positions. השתא נמי, hashta
nami, you know what? You're stuck here anyway even with all your
everything you've answered so far. קשיא דרבי יוחנן אדרבי יוחנן. kashya d'rabbi
yochanan a'drabbi yochanan. You got רבי יוחנן rabbi yochanan to say that
the guy would say it in the morning, right? So while it
was still under his control, which would be a ברירה breira position.
So now רבי יוחנן rabbi yochanan has to hold of ברירה breira
according to the way you framed it. We got a problem. רבי
יוחנן rabbi yochanan doesn't hold of ברירה. breira. Okay, so right you
got it in this case it's one or the other. Either you
can redeem something when it's not under your control or you do
it in the morning and then it's ברירה. breira. So you moved
רבי יוחנן rabbi yochanan into the morning position in order and he's
going to say ברירה, breira, but רבי יוחנן rabbi yochanan doesn't hold
of ברירה. breira. So קשיא דרבי יוחנן אדרבי יוחנן דאמרת לרבי יוחנן
לא תימא כל הנלקט kashya d'rabbi yochanan a'drabbi yochanan d'amarta l'rabbi yochanan
lo teima kol hanilkat
you said for רבי יוחנן rabbi yochanan don't say everything that was
picked and therefore it works after it's out of his control אלא
אימא כל המתלקט ela eima kol hamitlaket anything that will be taken
אלמא אית ליה ברירה. alma is lei breira. So now you've said
rather than having him say the אינו ברשותו eino b'reshuso position you
can do it when it's not in your רשות, reshus, you had
him do it to take effect in the morning which is a
ברירה breira position. But that doesn't work. אלמא אית ליה ברירה. alma
is lei breira. You're saying he holds of ברירה. breira. והא רבי
יוחנן לית ליה ברירה. v'ha rabbi yochanan leis lei breira. But רבי
יוחנן rabbi yochanan doesn't hold of ברירה. breira. דאמר רבי אסי אמר
רבי יוחנן האחים שחלקו d'amar rabbi assi amar rabbi yochanan ha'achim shechalku
if brothers when they divided an estate. Okay, so here's the question.
After brothers divide now there's different degrees of ברירה. breira. There's a
ברירה breira where you designate at the outset and say I am
מפריש תרומות ומעשרות mafrish terumos u'maasros on stuff to be designated later.
I am מפקיר mafkir stuff that will be identified later, right? There's
other types of ברירה breira where you didn't say any that's almost
like a תנאי. tnai. You know, there's other types of ברירה breira
where you didn't say anything and it's more of a deterministic type
of a way of looking at the world. The way things work
out in the end, we will say retroactively that was always the
way they were going to work out. Okay, and that comes up
in the following scenario where you have brothers are dividing an estate
they inherited from their father. Okay, what was the state of let's
say one takes the north field and the other takes the south
field? What was the state of that property before it was divided?
Was it jointly owned or owned by the estate? So okay fine.
So was there a time when ראובן reuven owned 50 percent of
the north and the south field and שמעון shimon owned 50 percent
of both and then they basically swapped my interest in the north
field for your interest in the south field? Is that how it
worked, right? Or do we say none that's if you didn't hold
of ברירה. breira. There was a time when it was jointly owned
and then there was a way and time in which they sort
of one person took part and the other took part and they
sort of waived, you know, or swapped, you know, their rights in
the other part of it. But if you hold of יש ברירה,
yesh breira, you would say ah now that you've divided it this
way, we see that even before you split it that was the
half that was going to ראובן reuven and that was the half
that was going to שמעון. shimon. What's the relevance of it? The
relevance of this is let's take a look. דאמר רבי אסי אמר
רבי יוחנן d'amar rabbi assi amar rabbi yochanan האחים שחלקו ha'achim shechalku
after brothers have divided an estate
לקוחות הן lekuchos hen we view it that they've bought each other
out of the other half of the estate ומחזירים זה לזה u'machazirin
zeh lazeh and if they're buyers was by יובל. Yovel. So then,
every time the יובל Yovel comes, everything also always reverts back because
it's like a purchase and any purchases revert back, which is crazy
because it's all talk about יובל Yovel being a type of a
restorative thing. Here it's going to restore things all the way back
to the people who entered in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael at the
time of יהושע, Yehoshua, because any division that has occurred since then
is all a type of a purchase even if it's stuff that's
been directly inherited, right? So anyway, it all goes back and now
has to get redivided. You have to find out all the ten
thousand members of your family and redivide the estate.
So anyway, that's what רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says, but you see
that he doesn't hold of ברירה. breira. So if he doesn't hold
of ברירה, breira, you cannot say that you're saying this thing in
the morning.
אלא לעולם ella le-olam fine, כל יניקה, kol yenika, you got me.
He doesn't hold of ברירה, breira, he's not saying it in the
morning, he's saying it after it got picked and he's saying anything
that got picked already. Now how can he do that? It's not
in his רשות. reshut. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan סתמא דמתניתין
אשכח.
stama de-matnitin
ashkech. Now that we're going back and not trying to switch things
around, רש״י Rashi says we can also have רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
say his normal position and we don't have to switch רבי יהודה.
Rebbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda could say that you also do
it in the day. And the question about how does רבי יהודה,
Rebbi Yehuda, doesn't he not hold of ברירה? breira? So רש״י Rashi
quotes another גמרא Gemara that says that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda does
hold of ברירה, breira, but he doesn't want you to be doing
this תרומות ומעשרות Terumot u-Ma'asrot thing because either you might drink it
all or the חבית chavit might break and the wine might not
be there at the end. Right exactly. So therefore there are other
reasons not to be doing it in the case of the תרומות
ומעשרות, Terumot u-Ma'asrot, but that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda actually does hold
of ברירה. breira. So we could put everything back to the way
it was. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda holds of ברירה, breira, you do
it in the morning. רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi holds it then in
the evening. The צנועים ha-Tzenuim are doing it in the evening. הצנועים
ha-Tzenuim and רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi say the same thing. You do
it in the evening after it's out of your control. Everything is
without switching things around. So what does רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan do?
Because now you're doing it out of your control. So the answer
is רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan doesn't פסקן pasken like the צנועים. ha-Tzenuim.
Now how is he allowed to do that? רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
says we rule like a סתם משנה. stam Mishnah. So the גמרא
Gemara says רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan סתמא דמתניתין אשכח. stama de-matnitin ashkech.
He found another סתם משנה. stam Mishnah. Yes, the צנועים ha-Tzenuim and
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi say you do it in the evening when
it's out of your control, but he found another סתם משנה. stam
Mishnah. דתנן, de-tenan, we taught in a משנה: Mishnah: אינו גונב אחר
גנב משלם תשלומי כפל. eino gonev achar ganav meshalem tashlumei khefel. So
it's our משנה, Mishnah, meaning רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says it's all
nice, the צנועים ha-Tzenuim and רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yossi, but our משנה
Mishnah teaches a different principle. So it says that the גנב ganav
doesn't have to pay the owner when he steals it out of
the house of another גנב. ganav. אמאי? amai? Why is that true?
בשלמא לגנב ראשון לא משלם, bishlama le-ganav rishon lo meshalem, I understand
why גנב ganav two doesn't pay גנב ganav one.
וגונב מבית האיש ולא מבית הגנב ve-gunav mi-beit ha-ish ve-lo mi-beit ha-ganav
because it doesn't, you don't even have to go to a פסוק.
pasuk. It's not, the גנב ganav doesn't own it. אלא לבעלים נשלם?
ella la-be'alim nishlem? Why not pay the owners? אלא שמע מינה: ella
shema mina: זה לפי שאינו שלו וזה לפי שאינו ברשותו. zeh lefi
she-eino shelo ve-zeh lefi she-eino bi-reshuto.
That one doesn't get paid because it's not his, and the other,
the owners don't get paid because it's not under the owner's control.
Meaning I am going to choose to read this not as some
arbitrary exemption in the תורה. Torah. I'm going to say if they're
not paying כפל, khefel, that must mean because הלכתית halachicly your ownership
of that object has somehow been impaired. You understand, רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan is basically saying you could run into a גזירת הכתוב. gezeirat
ha-katuv. You only get כפל khefel if it's in your house, if
it's under your control. No, the logic is it's telling you when
it's out of your control, your ownership is impaired. And therefore for
him the obvious consequence of that is, now you could say, okay,
impaired in what way, but he says no, to me it's obvious
the implicit point of the משנה Mishnah is that once it's out
of your control, you don't have any, you can't exercise your rights
as an
owner in that state. And therefore I would rather go by what
I understand is implicit in our משנה Mishnah and forget about the
צנועים ha-Tzenuim and forget about רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yossi. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara is going to say why do you choose one משנה
Mishnah over the other? ומה חזית דאזלת בתר האי סתמא? u-mah chazit
de-azlat batar hai stama? Why are you going by that סתם, stam,
our סתם משנה? stam Mishnah? לעביד כי האי סתמא דצנועים. la'avid ki
hai stama de-Tzenuim.
Follow the צנועים's ha-Tzenuim approach. They feel that you can do stuff
once it's out of your control. גמרא Gemara says no. משום דמסייע
ליה קרא mishum de-mesayei lei kra
because there's a פסוק pasuk that supports it, at least by הקדש,
hekdesh, which is where רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan started from. ואיש כי
יקדיש את ביתו קודש לה׳. ve-ish ki yakdish et beito kodesh l-Hashem.
If a man sanctifies his house to God. מה ביתו ברשותו, mah
beito bi-reshuto, the same way your house is under your control, אף
כל ברשותו. af kol bi-reshuto. So it has to be under your
control. And remember by the way, רבי יוחנן's Rebbi Yochanan original statement
was only that you can't sanctify something out of your control. So
one could actually say that the גמרא Gemara made this whole problem,
because maybe רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan only said his thing by הקדש,
hekdesh, and who knows how broad to apply the problem of אינו
ברשותו? eino bi-reshuto? But by הקדש hekdesh it has that keyword ביתו.
beito. By גנב ganav it says וגונב מבית האיש, ve-gunav mi-beit ha-ish,
and by הקדש hekdesh it says איש כי יקדיש את ביתו. ish
ki yakdish et beito. So maybe what רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is
saying is anytime the תורה Torah says there's an idea of ביתו,
beito, it doesn't work if it's stolen. But maybe he's not saying
it in all areas. But the גמרא Gemara abstracts רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan even further and
רבי יוחנן... Rebbi Yochanan... So maybe you understand how he learns it
from הקדש. hekdesh. So maybe it's not enough to learn it from
גנב. ganav. But if גנב ganav teaches me that you can't be
מקדיש, makdish, well why can't you be מקדיש makdish it? It must
mean that being מקדיש makdish it, doing something, transferring ownership, redeeming it,
selling it, these are things that are your, you know, your rights
or exercising your rights of an owner, and that you can't do
when it's out of your control. So if you can't do הקדש,
hekdesh, you can't do all these things. And that's the way רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan goes, and he'd rather follow that than follow the
צנועים. Tnu'im. Now, I want to pause for a moment and say
the following, which is that
even if I sort of say that logically you can't do certain
things that exercise your rights as an owner, if you can't be
מקדיש makdish it, you can't sell it. Selling it would be the
next obvious step. It's not so clear, and תוספות Tosafot points this
out, in a way the גמרא Gemara will point out in a
minute, that that would mean the two things we had just discussed.
Because what were the two things we applied רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
to? One is to redeem something, right, the מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
out of my control, the כרם רבעי kerem revai out of my
control, and the other is to be מפקיר mafkir the עניים ani'im
steal the grain they weren't allowed and I'm מפקיר mafkir it. So
it would seem to, it would seem that those things are things
that require a lot less of a status of an owner to
do. Why? Because to redeem it, תוספות Tosafot actually develops this, there's
a lot of times that you can redeem
stuff that isn't yours. If Michael sanctifies his house, I can go
ahead and redeem it. Okay? So, now this is a little different.
If it's כרם רבעי, kerem revai, Michael still has the right, it's
still Michael's fruit, he has the right to eat it in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, but I'm not taking the fruit away, I'm just redeeming it,
I'm just transferring the קדושה kedusha and making it available for him
to now eat as he wants. Maybe you don't have to be
the owner to redeem the כרם רבעי. kerem revai. So maybe it's
not the same type of agreement, right?
I want to bring it up to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you've redeemed it
now.
Right, so that's, so okay, so that's sort of what תוספות Tosafot
discusses, but you could have
imagined that it doesn't require the same, but you now are the
owner who's doing it. So the point is, selling something or sanctifying
something is a full exercise of ownership, you're transferring title. Here, you're
just removing the קדושה. kedusha. Maybe you don't have to have a
full, your full powers as owner, maybe you can do it when
it's out of your control. Also the idea of הפקר. hefker. Now
הפקר hefker you could say is a type of like transferring title.
I transfer title away from me to everyone or something like that.
Maybe you do need full status. But you could say the opposite,
if it's out of my control, it's easier to be מפקיר mafkir
it because I'm just removing my rights further. It's halfway out of
my control and I'm pulling away the other half. So it's interesting
even if רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is to be abstracted, that you
need it under your control to really, you know, be a full
owner and do a full things that owners do, it's not clear
that everything gets thrown into the same category. Okay, and תוספות Tosafot
basically makes these points. But the גמרא Gemara was comparing all of
it. So let's now continue in the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא
Gemara says like
this: אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, אי לאו דאמר רבי
יוחנן צנועים ורבי דוסא אמרו דבר אחד, Ilov de'amar Rabbi Yochanan Tnu'im
v'Rabbi Dosa amru davar echad, צנועים Tnu'im and רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa
were saying the same thing, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would have
said, צנועים אית להו דרבי דוסא, Tnu'im is lehu d'Rabbi Dosa, the
צנועים Tnu'im would agree with רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa about being מפקיר
mafkir
if they're going to pick up the grain, you know, too much
grain, ורבי דוסא
לית ליה דצנועים, v'Rabbi Dosa leis lei d'Tnu'im, but רבי דוסא Rabbi
Dosa would not necessarily agree with the צנועים. Tnu'im. Why?
צנועים, Tnu'im, and this is less of an issue about your ability
to do it and being מפקיר mafkir or redeeming something that's not
under your control, and more over whether you should be doing it
or not. So let's take a look. צנועים אית להו דרבי דוסא
וצנועים מודו דרבי דוסא, Tnu'im is lehu d'Rabbi Dosa v'Tnu'im modei d'Rabbi
Dosa, ומה בגנב עבדו רבנן תקנתא, u'ma be'ganav avdu rabanan takanta,
עניים צריך למימר? ani'im tzarich l'meimar? If they are making a תקנתא,
takanta, if you know, you are so pious that you think, that
you're prepared for somebody who's a גנב ganav steals into your orchard
of כרם רבעי kerem revai and stealing your fruit and you still
don't want them to eat the כרם רבעי kerem revai and you're
so concerned, certainly the עניים ani'im that have a right to be
there and are just picking up the grain and might pick up
a few extra stalks, they're going to have רחמנות rachmanus on them
and you're going to want them to not steal and you're going
to want to be מפקיר. mafkir. So clearly you'll be motivated to
do it in that case. Okay, but ורבי דוסא לית ליה דצנועים,
v'Rabbi Dosa leis lei d'Tnu'im, okay, but I would say, I'm
sorry, רבי דוסא, Rabbi Dosa, just because he's motivated to do the
being מפקיר mafkir the grain doesn't mean he'd be motivated in the
צנועים Tnu'im case. עניים הוא דעבדו להו רבנן תקנתא, Ani'im hu de'avdu
lehu rabanan takanta, by the עניים ani'im the rabbis made a תקנתא,
takanta, since you know, they basically have a right to be there,
they're just picking up a few extra stalks, אבל גנב, aval ganav,
guy steals into your orchard, לא עבדו ליה רבנן תקנתא, lo avdu
lei rabanan takanta, they did not do anything for him. Okay. So
I would not have put them in the same category. אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, אי לאו דאמר רבי יוחנן צנועים ורבי
דוסא אמרו דבר אחד, Ilov de'amar Rabbi Yochanan Tnu'im v'Rabbi Dosa amru
davar echad, he's going to have another take on this, had רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan not said they said the same thing, הוה אמינא,
hava amina, I would have said, מאן תנא צנועים רבי מאיר היא.
man tana Tnu'im? Rabbi Meir hi. That maybe the צנועים, Tnu'im, and
this is essentially what I said a minute
ago, maybe the צנועים Tnu'im have nothing to do, are not a
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan problem. It's not a problem that it's out
of your control. Why is it not a problem that it's out
of your control if you're going to redeem it? Because maybe they're
following רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. What's רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? לאו
אמר רבי מאיר מעשר ממון גבוה הוא? Lav amar Rabbi Meir maaser
mammon gavoha hu? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that מעשר שני maaser
sheni is not, you're not the owner of מעשר שני. maaser sheni.
You have a right to eat it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but you're
not considered the owner of it. And כרם רבעי kerem revai is
the same status of מעשר שני. maaser sheni. It has to be
eaten in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that קדושה
kedusha takes it out of your ownership. You still have rights to
it but it takes it out of your ownership. And so, how
do you redeem it? So the גמרא Gemara says, ואפילו הכי, ve-afilu
hachi, even though you don't technically own it, לענין פדיה אוקמה רחמנא
ברשותיה. le-inyan pidyah u-kma rachmana bi-rshutei. The Torah considered it yours if
you're coming to redeem it, even though it's technically not yours.
דכתיב, de-chtiv, and if it's מעשר maaser at
all, it's just,
no, מעשר שני maaser sheni specifically. דכתיב ואם גאל יגאל איש ממעשרו,
de-chtiv ve-im gaol yigal ish mi-maasro, if a person redeems his מעשר,
maaser, this is only מעשר שני, maaser sheni, חמישיתו יוסף עליו, chamishito
yosef alav, you add a fifth. So now what we're saying is,
I know you're doing it as an owner, because if another person
redeems a מעשר, maaser, he wouldn't add a fifth. But when you
do it, you're adding a fifth. So you see that the Torah,
it's sort of like חמץ chametz on פסח, Pesach, it's not really
yours, the Torah considers it yours. This isn't really yours, but if
you redeem it, the Torah considers it yours and gives you this
extra fifth. Okay,
קריה רחמנא מעשרו, karya rachmana maasro, they call it your מעשר, maaser,
ומוסיף חומש, u-mosif chamesh, and you have to add a fifth. So
כרם רבעי נמי, kerem revai nami, so כרם רבעי kerem revai as
well, גמר קודש קודש ממעשר, gmar kodesh kodesh mi-maaser, it's linked to
מעשר. maaser. כתיב הכא קודש הלולים, ktiv hacha kodesh hillulim, holy
rejoicing to God, וכתיב גבי מעשר וכל מעשר הארץ מזרע הארץ מפרי
העץ לה׳ הוא קודש קודש לה׳, u-chtiv gabei maaser ve-chol maaser ha-aretz
mi-zera ha-aretz mi-pri ha-etz la-Shem hu kodesh kodesh la-Shem, I think it
is. So מה קודש דכתיב גבי מעשר, ma kodesh de-chtiv gabei maaser,
so the same way the holiness by מעשר maaser means אף על
גב דממון גבוה הוא, af al gav de-mammon gavoha hu, even though
it's sanctified and it's God's, לענין פדיה אוקמה רחמנא ברשותיה, le-inyan pidyah
u-kma rachmana bi-rshutei, when it comes to redeeming it the Torah treated
it as if it's yours. אף האי קודש נמי דכתיב גבי כרם
רבעי, af hai kodesh nami de-chtiv gabei kerem revai, by כרם רבעי
kerem revai as well, אף על גב דלאו ממון דידיהו הוא, af
al gav de-lav mammon di-deihu hu, it's not yours, it's sanctified,
לענין אחלולי אוקמה רחמנא ברשותיה, le-inyan achlolei u-kma rachmana bi-rshutei, the Torah
treated it yours. Now here's finally the kicker. It's a long way
of saying that when you're redeeming it, you're not really the owner,
but the Torah is treating you as the owner. Okay, if that's
true, then maybe it doesn't matter that it's not under your control
and that it's been stolen, because it wasn't yours anyway and the
Torah treated it as if it's yours.
So okay,
דהא כי איתא ברשותיה
נמי הלאו דידיה הוא ומצי מחלי, de-ha ki itei bi-rshutei nami hala
di-deihu hu u-matzei machlei, so even when, meaning
the
אוקמה רחמנא ברשותיה u-kma rachmana bi-rshutei means, even when it is in
your house, נמי לאו דידיה, nami lav di-deihu, it's really not yours
anyway, okay, but the Torah considers something not yours yours to let
you redeem it. It'll consider something not into your control as if
it's under your control. So maybe redeeming is a long way of
saying that redeeming does not require the full status and the full
powers of ownership. You don't anyway have the full powers by this;
it's קודש, kodesh, you have to eat it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and
so on. So you can redo it even out of your control.
דהא כי איתא ברשותיה... de-ha ki itei bi-rshutei... so okay, ומצי מחלי
משום
הכי מצי מחלי, u-matzei machlei mi-shum hachi matzei machlei, therefore you can
redeem it. אבל גבי לקט, aval gabei leket, but when it comes
to לקט, leket, כיון דממונא דידיה, keivan de-mammona di-deihu, when it's your
money, כי איתא ברשותיה הוא דמצי מפקר ליה, ki itei bi-rshutei hu
de-matzei mafkir lei, you can renounce ownership, מפקיר mafkir something that is
your property, that is under your control, וכי ליתא ברשותיה לא מצי
מפקר ליה, ve-ki leitah bi-rshutei lo matzei mafkir lei, but when it's
not under your control, you can't be מפקיר mafkir it. So therefore
I would have said that, and I would have solved the צנועים
tznuim problem for רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. What he's actually also saying
is that, you know, we said oh the צנועים tznuim they're not
like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, you can do it out of your
control. He says no, no, no, that's by מעשר, maaser, that's by
redeeming. Redeeming you don't have to be the full owner in order
to, you know, you're never the full owner anyway. So you don't
have to have it under your control in order to redeem it.
The only person that doesn't work with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is
רבי דוסא, Rabbi Dosa, because he's having you be מפקיר mafkir it
when it's out of your control, and that he says does require
the full status of ownership. Now I would say depends how you
look at הפקר. hefker. If הפקר hefker is like transferring title away
from me to no one, maybe it does require, you're transferring title,
you need the full status of ownership. But if it's just removing
yourself, I would think if it's already halfway removed, just, you know,
finish the thing on your own.
And then maybe things we also don't say.
We don't say because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan put them in the
same category. But then רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying we don't
rule like those two, the way the גמרא Gemara is framing it,
we rule against them because and go like our משנה. mishna. So
now the גמרא Gemara just continues this point, one other reason why
I would not have had to, I would not have put them
together. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, אי לאו דאמר רבי יוחנן צנועים ורבי
דוסא אמרו דבר אחד, i-lav de-amar Rabbi Yochanan tznuim ve-Rabbi Dosa amru
davar echad, הוה אמינא, hava amina, if he had not said they
said one thing, I would have said: מאן תנא צנועים רבי דוסא
היא! man tanna tznuim Rabbi Dosa hi! It's not that they're two
different opinions that happen to be agreeing. That the רבי דוסא Rabbi
Dosa shows us, the רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa statement by the לקט
leket and by the הפקר hefker shows us. that he's the one
that believes you can do this stuff in the evening and so
on even out of your control. So he must be the one
who's been teaching this idea about the תנויי. t'nuim. And then it's
no longer a סתם משנה. stam mishnah. Then it's we've discovered that
really is a single opinion. Okay, קשיא דרבי יוחנן אדרבי יוחנן סתם
משנה לרבי יוחנן רבי יוחנן כי סתם יחידא לא אמר. kashya d'Rabbi
Yochanan a'Rabbi Yochanan stam mishnah l'Rabbi Yochanan Rabbi Yochanan ki stam yachida
lo amar. Even if it's taught סתם, stam, if it's a סתם
יחידא, stam yachida, if it's סתם stam that we know is the
opinion of a minority opinion, then it is or of a single
opinion, it is not authoritative, even if it's taught in an anonymous
voice. So I could have got out of that by saying, oh
yeah, I mean instead of saying רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan preferred one
סתם stam over another, I could have said that was really just
a דעת יחיד da'at yachid anyway. Okay, so really fascinating idea that
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan takes the idea that you don't pay כפל,
kefel, chooses to see that that is not a limited הלכה halacha
by a גנב, ganav, but it reflects an idea of an owner's
control, בעלו, ba'alo, learns by הקדש hekdesh that you can't be מקדיש
makdish if it's not under your control. If it's not under your
control, you can't exercise your full rights as an owner. And then
abstracts it or the גמרא, Gemara, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan never really
abstracted it, but the גמרא Gemara abstracted it to say and therefore
you can't do other things that require you to be an owner.
You can't sell it, the גמרא Gemara doesn't even say that but
that should be obvious. You can't sell it, you can't give it,
and what the גמרא Gemara then extends it to which are the
things that are less obvious you needed the full status is you
can't be מפקיר mafkir and you can't redeem it. So and then
we had to try to figure out so he doesn't rule like
other תנאים Tannaim that say that you can. Yes.
Being יאוש ye'ush on something, doesn't it make it הפקר? hefker?
Exactly. So יאוש ye'ush is the classic example of it's out of
my control, I'm מייאש, m'ya'esh, I remove myself from it and that
therefore lets people come take possession of it and it's exactly that.
It's further separating yourself. It doesn't require ownership, it requires the weakening
of ownership. So basically what this is saying is is that yes,
the process, meaning it could be that after יאוש ye'ush it's considered
הפקר, hefker, although that's a debate of ראשונים Rishonim or the אחרונים
Acharonim want to frame it as a debate of the ראשונים. Rishonim.
If you lost an object and you were מייאש m'ya'esh and I
pick it up, at that moment is it still technically your object
but your control is so weakened that I'm allowed to take it?
Or do we say no at that stage after your יאוש ye'ush
it's not even your object? So that's a... so they make נפקא
מינות. nafka minos. So that might be a debate of the ראשונים.
Rishonim. Okay, but even if that's true that it is in a
state of הפקר hefker after your יאוש, ye'ush, the process is different.
יאוש ye'ush comes through right a weakening of your control, it's physically
out and then you've given up hope or whatever and it's so
whereas הפקר hefker comes from an active pushing it out of your
control, pushing it out of your ownership. So what this גמרא Gemara
is saying is a little a little ironic
even since הפקר hefker is that more active of an owner of
pushing it out, not separating, you can't do it if it's half
out of your control. Okay, so that's a... I mean it's a
חידוש chiddush because you could have said even with whatever הפקר hefker
is a different process since the end result is halfway there it's
you know it shouldn't be any harder to do. But that's anyway
the גמרא'ס Gemara's assertion.
Can't you also say though alright he's just... if he's מייאש... m'ya'esh...
So תוספות Tosafot discusses that. No, but יאוש ye'ush wouldn't work to
redeem it. יאוש ye'ush would not work for... wouldn't work for the
הפקר hefker case either. תוספות Tosafot discusses that you had to do
it through הפקר hefker obviously through הפקר. hefker.
Okay, so we'll pick up with this tomorrow.